<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researches on Rodrigo Dorantes Gilardi</title>
    <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Researches on Rodrigo Dorantes Gilardi</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://rodogi.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>AI and Scientific Knowledge</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/ai-scientific-knowledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/ai-scientific-knowledge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Large language models (LLMs) are rapidly becoming tools for scientific information retrieval, yet their ability to recognize scientists and their contributions is far from uniform. In this work, we audit how three leading LLMs—GPT-4o, Claude 3.5 Sonnet, and Gemini 1.5 Pro—recognize over 100,000 physicists across the productivity spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Our analysis reveals systematic disparities: LLMs are significantly better at recognizing male scientists and those affiliated with Western institutions, mirroring and amplifying existing biases in scientific visibility. We trace these gaps in part to Wikipedia, which serves as a key training source and exhibits similar patterns of coverage inequality. The findings highlight that as LLMs become embedded in scientific workflows—from literature search to peer review—they risk reinforcing the unequal recognition structures already present in academia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inspirational Cohorts</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/inspirational-cohorts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/inspirational-cohorts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What makes certain groups of people catalyze disproportionate creative or scientific output? This project, funded by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.templeton.org/grant/inspirational-cohorts-and-the-science-of-purpose&#34; &#xA;  &#xA;   target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34; &#xA;&gt;John Templeton Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, takes a data-driven approach to identifying and understanding inspirational cohorts—clusters of individuals whose collective interactions spark transformative ideas.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Combining network science, natural language processing, and large language models, the project pursues three interconnected goals: (1) mapping the structure and dynamics of inspirational communities across history, (2) understanding how cultural and institutional contexts shape the emergence of these cohorts, and (3) applying the Science of Purpose framework to uncover how shared purpose drives collective achievement.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NetMedPy</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/netmedpy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/netmedpy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Network medicine views diseases as localized disruptions in networks of genes, proteins, and other molecular entities, offering a framework to understand how biological systems communicate and fail. NetMedPy is an open-source Python package that streamlines large-scale network medicine analyses, enabling researchers to evaluate network localization, compute proximity and separation between biological entities, and screen thousands of drug–disease pairs efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The package extends traditional approaches by providing four built-in distance metrics (shortest paths, random walk, biased random walk, and communicability) and four null models (degree match, degree logarithmic binning, strength logarithmic binning, and uniform), while also supporting user-defined custom metrics. By leveraging precomputed distance matrices, NetMedPy optimizes calculations for large interactomes, making network medicine screening practical at scale.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biobanks</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/biobanks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/biobanks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Biobanks—large repositories of biological samples and associated health data—are fundamental to modern biomedical research, yet their contributions are poorly captured by traditional metrics. In this work, we systematically traced over 2,600 biobanks across nearly 230,000 documents, including scientific publications, patents, clinical trials, grants, and policy reports, to map the full scope of their influence on science and public health.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We introduced the Biobank Impact Factor (BIF), a multidimensional metric that goes beyond citation counts to quantify a biobank’s reach. The BIF integrates factors such as the diversity of diseases studied, translational footprint, and intensity of collaborative use. Our analysis shows that biobanks offering open access to external researchers and maintaining rich, longitudinal datasets linked to medical records tend to have significantly greater scientific impact.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BioTools</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/biotools/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/biotools/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Biomedical tools—laboratory methods, modeling techniques, and software applications—are essential to scientific discovery, from detecting genetic variants to visualizing molecular structures. Despite their critical role, these tools are frequently overlooked by traditional impact metrics such as citation counts, leaving a significant gap in recognizing the scientists and teams behind these innovations.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To address this, our &lt;a href=&#34;https://reporter.nih.gov/project-details/11120817&#34; &#xA;  &#xA;   target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noreferrer noopener&#34; &#xA;&gt;NIH-funded project&lt;/a&gt; establishes a comprehensive knowledge base, BioToolKB, that captures and categorizes the spectrum of BioTools used across biomedicine. By building a large, searchable repository linked to scientific publications, patents, clinical trials, and policy documents, we trace each tool’s reach and influence across science, policy, and clinical practice. We also develop new metrics that go beyond traditional indicators to capture BioTools’ contributions across sectors and their influence on disease research and treatment advancements.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Public procurement networks</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/procurement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/procurement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Public procurement networks represent the complex relationships between government entities and private contractors. Our research focuses on understanding these relationships and their impact on public spending efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;key-findings&#34;&gt;Key Findings&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Network structure reveals preferential attachments between certain contractors and government entities&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Community detection algorithms identify potential procurement clusters&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Temporal analysis shows evolution of procurement patterns&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://rodogi.github.io/images/favs.png&#34; alt=&#34;Procurement Network Visualization&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We applied several network analysis techniques:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Community detection&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Centrality measures&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Temporal evolution analysis&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-python&#34; data-lang=&#34;python&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# Example code snippet&lt;/span&gt;&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; networkx &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; nx&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;analyze_procurement_network&lt;/span&gt;(edges):&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    G &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; nx&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;Graph()&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    G&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;add_edges_from(edges)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    communities &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; nx&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;community&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;louvain_communities(G)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    centrality &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; nx&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;eigenvector_centrality(G)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; communities, centrality&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;publications&#34;&gt;Publications&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Structure and dynamics of public procurement networks&amp;rdquo; (2023)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Temporal evolution of contractor relationships&amp;rdquo; (2024)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;collaborators&#34;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dr. Jane Smith (Harvard University)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prof. John Doe (MIT)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Venue Effect</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/venue/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/venue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prominent venues—top journals in science, major biennials in art—act as gatekeepers that shape career trajectories. But who actually benefits from gaining access to these platforms? In this work, we reconstruct the full careers of 3.4 million scientists across physics, chemistry, biology, and sociology, alongside visual and performing artists, to quantify the causal impact of venue access on downstream career outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Using heterogeneous difference-in-differences analysis, we document a statistically significant and long-lasting venue effect in both science and the arts, and show that it is a relatively recent phenomenon—becoming a prominent force only after the 1990s. Critically, the benefits of venue access are neither universal nor equitable: they are modulated by career stage, gender, and geography.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crime and urban landscape</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/crime/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/crime/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization in social networks (Social)</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/polarization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/polarization/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gender networks</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/gender-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/gender-networks/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gene co-expression in breast cancer</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/gene-coexpression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/gene-coexpression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this study, we used a multilayer network approach to uncover fundamental structural principles in gene co-expression networks (GCNs) that are disrupted in breast cancer. By analyzing both healthy and cancerous gene co-expression networks, we identified key differences in connectivity patterns, revealing how healthy cells maintain a complex network of gene interactions across chromosomes. In contrast, the breast cancer network exhibits a loss of these inter-chromosomal connections, leading to a simpler, more localized structure confined largely to genes within the same chromosome.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protein Structure</title>
      <link>https://rodogi.github.io/research/protein-networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://rodogi.github.io/research/protein-networks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project looks into the structural and functional shifts in proteins caused by mutations, exploring how such changes impact protein behavior. By constructing detailed amino acid networks for five proteins, we analyzed how mutations at specific positions alter both structure and function, revealing a strong relationship between structural sensitivity and functional outcomes. Our approach combines network science with protein modeling, allowing us to predict functionally sensitive regions based solely on structural perturbations.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
